Guide to the Eugène and Maria Jolas Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
The Eugène Jolas Papers begin with Series I, Correspondence, which consists of letters to and from Eugène Jolas during the period 1910 (when he first moved to New York) to 1952 (the year he died). The earliest letters extant are those sent by the young Eugène to his family during his early years living in New York City, dating from 1910-1913. (These are filed under Jolas Family.) Written in German, these missives are accompanied by English translations done years later by Jolas or a secretary in preparation for his autobiography. Letters from his wife, Maria Jolas, cover the years 1939-1950. Eugène's letters to Maria are filed in Series VII, Correspondence of Maria Jolas. Other Jolas family members represented include Eugène's brothers Armand Jolas, Emile Jolas, and Jacques Jolas, and well as Christine Jolas, their mother. All of these letters date from 1935-1952, many of them written during World War II.
Among the literary personages in this first correspondence series are Kay Boyle, Malcolm Cowley, Raoul Hausmann, Klaus Mann, Blanche Matthias, Henry Miller, Anaïs Nin, Raymond Queneau, and Jean Wahl.
Series II, Writings, is the largest series in the Eugène Jolas Subgroup. The first subseries contains typescripts and printed versions of articles written by Eugène Jolas for various magazines and reviews between 1924-1951. Included are copies of his columns from 1924, "Rambles Through Literary Paris" and those from 1949-1950, "Across Frontiers." A number of his articles are criticisms of writers and movements, such as "Ernst Juenger et le crépuscule du nihilisme," "Surrealism: Ave atque Vale," and "Arts and Letters in Latin America." A number of articles concern James Joyce. They may be connected to works comprising the "Work on James Joyce" at the end of the next subseries, Books. Two manuscripts on Novalis are filed here as well, though they may be early versions of articles collected for the book, Novalis.
The second subseries, Books, makes up the greatest part of the Writings subseries. The main text here is Eugène Jolas' autobiography which he worked on for over a decade. Referred to in this archives as Man From Babel (one of several titles considered by Jolas) this work survives in several drafts, all unpublished, left by Jolas when he died in 1952. Due to the scattered nature of the material when it was received, an attempt has been made to generally group the chapter drafts which survived intact into broad time periods. The first texts filed here, however, are "German Diary" and "From a Frankfurt Notebook," loosely gathered notes and fragments that serve as very elementary versions of the autobiography. Following these are Drafts A through E, ordered by their apparent dates of creation. Each draft has most or all of the following divisions represented: Prologue, Childhood, Young Adulthood, Return to Lorraine, Reporter in Paris, New Orleans, Founding transition, 1930s, World War II, DENA, and Post-War. Included here are also draft fragments, which could not be matched with specific drafts, and miscellaneous pages and poems intended for inclusion in the work.
This autobiography provides various details about stages of Eugène Jolas' life. At times confessional, and at others very analytic, Man From Babel provides an account of his journalistic career and success in publishing transition before serving as a military writer and editor during World War II. The autobiography proceeds linearly, from Jolas' childhood in Lorraine, through his time in Paris, and up to his work with DENA, concentrating at length on his later accomplishments, while providing details about the entire transition era.
Other Books represented in this subseries include drafts of Der Moderne Reporter, which Eugène Jolas wrote at the request of the Information Services Division of the occupational government in Germany and War, about his experiences as a military newsman. "Work on James Joyce" consists of several articles and profiles which Jolas apparently intended to gather together for a volume about Joyce. Several outlines and notes for others works are included here as well.
The following subseries contains Eugène Jolas' poetry. His poems had were sorted and organized after his death by his widow and her arrangement has been respected here. The first section, Books of Poems, reflects volumes actually published by Jolas, or groups of manuscripts and typescripts gathered together by Maria Jolas with the intention of being published as books. Most of Eugène Jolas' published books of poetry are extant here, except for his earliest works, Ink, Cinema, Succession in Astropolis and his later volumes I Have Seen Monsters and Angels, Mots-Déluge, The Language of Night, and Angels and Demons.
The four unpublished collections of poems are Lorraine Poem, Poems About Stars and Planets, Reporters, and Selected Poems. ( Wanderpoem did appear in a limited edition in 1946, published in Wiesbaden by Transition Press.) The poems which make up each of these proposed volumes have been kept in the order in which they were originally filed, with individual poem titles or incipits listed. The spelling, especially in terms of accents and capitalization, follows the manuscript. The poems within Reporters fall into a number of sections and subheadings, which have been retained as to the basic hierarchy. Most of the poems are undated, except for a number in Selected Poems, because they had been published previously.
The next section of poems, Poems as Organized by Maria Jolas, has also been kept in original order. Maria Jolas and a secretary classified Jolas' poems according to language: English, French, German, and Multilingual Poem. Titles and incipits have been listed in agreement with the Master Lists compiled at the time. Multilingual refers to the poems written in Atlantica, the polyglot Eugène Jolas invented.
The remaining poems in this series, Other Poems, are those which were not previously catalogued by Maria Jolas. They include many of Jolas' single published poems from his native language newspaper, Stimmen aus Lothringen. Also here are various fragments, titled and untitled found among his papers.
Three small subseries complete the Books series. Speeches contains a program noting a speech by Eugène Jolas on James Joyce. Stories contains two short pieces, one published and one in typescript form. The last subseries is Writings of Others. Most of the works included here appear to be drafts of stories and articles by reporters working for Jolas when he edited German newspapers after World War II. A number of pieces by authors such as Swedenborg, Tolstoy, Hugo, Blaise Cendrars, and Martin Buber are typescript versions of essays and clippings Jolas may have used in preparing critical articles.
In Series III, Translations, the principal is Novalis, a collections of translations accompanied by critical essays by Eugène Jolas. The other translations filed here are Nadja by André Breton, Earthwalker by Dorothy Donnelly, Les Chimères, Les Filles du Feu, and Aurelia, by Gérard de Nerval, and a French Catholic Anthology of mystical poets. Though Eugène Jolas did a large number of translations during his most productive years, only these few titles survive in the archives.
Materials concerning Jolas' career as a military journalist are contained in Series IV, DENA (the Deutsche Allgemeine Nachrichten Agentur "DANA", but known in English as DENA). Writings by Eugène Jolas, in the form of articles produced for various newspapers, and a draft, in English, of a "Journalism textbook", can be found here. Articles by other reporters are extant, as well. A number of publications, from DENA, from the United States Government, and from miscellaneous outside sources are filed in this subseries. Various working documents, such as government information circulars and memoranda have been retained. Specific wartime memorabilia and documents can be found here. Specifically, the employment application assessments detail the political histories of Germans who attempted to apply for positions with DENA. Housed in the Oversize boxes are propaganda posters showing scenes from concentration camps, accompanied by German texts.
Series V, Personal Papers, concerns Eugène Jolas. Included here are profiles of Jolas, the majority of which were written in tribute to him after his death. Scripts of a tribute by Radio Strasbourg from 1957 are also filed here. The remainder of this small series consists of items such as notes, tax documents, legal papers, and horoscopes.
The final series in the Eugène Jolas subgroup is Series VI, Photographs. This is the only series which gathers together like materials from the papers of both Maria and Eugène Jolas, for ease of reference. Eugène Jolas appears in photographic prints dating from 1910, in New York with brother Jacques, through a final portrait from 1951. The Jolas family from Forbach is documented here. Maria Jolas appears in some early portraits and several later poses with her grandchildren and colleagues during the 1970s and 1980s. Group photographs include many members of the Jolas' extended family from the late 1930s, including Henri Matisse, Barbara Constant, Mara Thaon, and Georges Pelorson.
The second subgroup, Maria Jolas Papers, consists of five series which, for the most part, parallel those in the Eugène Jolas group. The first of these is Series VII, Correspondence, which includes letters to and from a wide-range of people and organizations spanning from 1935 to 1986. Eugène's letters to Maria, from the period 1938-1951, during which the couple spent the majority of their time apart, are found here. Eugène writes candidly from New York, London, Occupied France, and Frankfurt. Other family members are represented by series of letters. Eugène's brothers Armand and Jacques are included, as are Jacques' wife and daughter Helen and Helène. Eugène's sister Maria Dillenschneider (wife of Celestin Dillenschneider) corresponded with Maria throughout the 1940s and into the 1950s. Maria's own family, scattered throughout the United States, wrote to Maria for several decades. Found here are letters to her sisters Laetitia Irwin and Cornelia Pemberton, and those to her brother Donald McDonald (along with his wife Josie). Both of Maria's daughters, Betsy and Tina, are represented by more recent letters. Also included are examples of letters from members of their respective families.
This series also includes letters from James Joyce and his family. Those from James Joyce himself date from the final years of his life, when Maria Jolas was closely involved with his welfare. Correspondence with Nora and George Joyce continued after James' death in 1942, often concerning their financial difficulties and the status of James Joyce's estate. The greatest bulk of letters survive from artist and writer friends Maria and Eugène Jolas knew from their work on the literary scene for over four decades, such as Sylvia Beach, Samuel Beckett, Kay Boyle (who included a typescript of her story "Approchez-vous Mesdames" in an early letter), Alexander and Louisa Calder, René Char, Padraic Colum, Carola Giedion-Welcker, Yvan and Claire Goll, Peggy Guggenheim, Paul and Lucie Léon, Jean-Jacques Mayoux, Nathalie Sarraute, John Slocum, Frances Steloff, James Stern, Pierre Vidal-Naquet, and Jean Wahl, among others.
Family friends of Maria and Eugène Jolas, the Duthuit family, Georges, Marguerite, and Claude, are represented here. Marguerite's family, the Matisses, Amélie, Henri, and Pierre, also corresponded with Maria Jolas, often concerning the welfare of young Claude Duthuit, who was under the care of the Jolas family in the early years of World War II. Another French family with whom Maria had a long relationship are the Massons, represented here by letters from André and Rose. Correspondence between Maria and Joyce scholars, with whom she had interactions ranging from very pleasant to quite difficult, constitute a large part of the correspondence from the 1960s through the 1980s. Among these researchers who wrote asking for Maria's assistance are Bernard Benstock, Helène Cixous, Richard Ellmann, Richard Kain, Richard Kearney, Fritz Senn, and Thomas Staley. Maria's work as a translator accounts for most of the correspondence with publishing companies, much of which concerns technical matters involving her work on texts. Examples of these are André Sauret, George Braziller, Inc., John Calder Publishers, Inc., and Orion Press.
The Third Party correspondence contains a relatively small number of items sent between persons whose own correspondence is represented, for the most part, in the General correspondence. Among those writing and receiving letters are: George Duthuit, from Marguerite Duthuit and Amélie Matisse; Richard Ellmann, from Carola Giedion-Welcker; Betsy Jolas, from George Duthuit; Tina Jolas, from Maria Dillenschneider and Georges and Claude Duthuit; Nora Joyce, from Edmund Brauchbar and Sylvia Sax; F. Lionel Monro, from Nora Joyce; and the United States Embassy, from James Joyce.
The next series in the Maria Jolas subgroup is Series VIII, Writings. As her husband had done, Maria began working on an autobiography in her later years. Her work, also unpublished at the time of her death, was more concise than Eugène's. The drafts of her untitled autobiography are divided between early drafts and later drafts. Within each of these, chapters are arranged by time period. In specific, early drafts contain sections relating to Childhood, Schooling, Sailing to Germany, Studying in Germany, and Life at Colombey. Later drafts contain sections relating to Berlin to Paris, Paris, 1919-1927, and Enddream.
A number of articles written by Maria Jolas comprise the next section of Writings. Many of these concerning James Joyce were published in scholarly journals. Several articles concerning French culture and theater were written for annual issues of the Encyclopedia Britannica Yearbook during the late 1940s and early 1950s. The subject of her other writings includes childhood education and France during wartime.
The remainder of this series consists of smaller subseries. Included here are Notebooks concerning episodes during Maria's life, specifically the École bilingue de Neuilly, the final days at St. Gérand-le Puy during the fall of France, and her war diary. The Open Letters subseries contains letters written by Maria to groups of friends or for general publication in widely read magazines and newspapers. Poems consists of two short pieces written late in Maria's life. The Program, "Récits et chants du folklore américain" was written for presentation to French children. Maria's Radio Addresses documents her efforts during the early years of World War II to speak on behalf of France and the French people. Such speeches as "The Fight for Freedom Committee" and "The French Home" were broadcast by stations in the New York City area. Of the four Speeches filed here, three were prepared in the early 1940s, while one was presented during the Joyce centenary celebration in 1982.
Writings of Others includes a printed work by Yvan Goll, "Chansons de France," a draft, with corrections, of Dougald McMillan's history, Transition: The History of a Literary Era, 1927-1938, an extract of a letter by Charles Jolas as well as typescripts of works by Richard Kearney and J. S. O'Leary, and Pierre Vidal-Naquet.
Series IX, Translations, contains translations done by Maria Jolas from the 1940s through the 1970s. Correspondence which was included with texts and notebooks as they were received have been kept with the texts they concern. (See also: Series VII, Correspondence - Publishers) The largest number of complete texts, both in French and in English translation, are for works by Nathalie Sarraute. Sarraute's first novel Portrait d'un inconnu is included in several translation drafts. Most of Sarraute's works from the 1960s and 1970s translated by Maria Jolas are included here, from the novels Le Planetarium and Disent les imbéciles, to the plays Le Silence and Le Mensonge, to the critical article broadcast on French radio "Flaubert le Précurseur."
Maria Jolas' work with other French writers in reflected in materials concerning her work on Robert Jaulin's examination of African culture, La Mort Sara, René Char's Chants de la Balandrane, Gaston Bachelard's Poétique de l'espace, and Georges Bataille's "The Economic Role of the Gift: Potlatch." Maria Jolas did a number of translations of books about artists and art movements during the late 1950s and 1960s, as well. Represented here are The Lithographs of Chagall by Julien Cain, Constantin Brancusi by Carola Giedion-Welcker, and several works by André Masson. Her work in German to English translation is represented by the collection of poems by Hugo von Hofmannsthal. Among Maria's several translations of works by Pierre Vidal-Naquet is his A Paper Eichmann, complete with background clippings about the controversy surrounding the confrontation that led to Vidal-Naquet's book.
Included in this series is a book that contains work from several writers. What was referred to in her files as the "Multilingual Poets Project" was an anthology Maria Jolas prepared to present the poems of her husband and several other poets who regularly composed verse in more than one language. Represented here are typescripts of poems by Yvan Goll, Edouard Roditi, Eugène Jolas, and Jean Wahl. Filed at the end of this series are materials relating to Maria Jolas' winning of the Scott Moncrieff Prize in 1971.
In Series X, Subject Files, the vast majority of material concerns James Joyce. Maria Jolas spent a great deal of energy following Joyce's death collecting writings about him and documenting societies, symposia, films, and meetings dedicated to him. The articles included here are, in general, offprints and photocopies of typescripts presented to Maria with autographs from the authors. Among the Joyce scholars represented here are Bernard and Shari Benstock, Helène Cixous, Richard Ellmann, Richard M. Kain, Joseph Prescott, and Fritz Senn. Special Joyce issues of magazines are files here, including a run of The Analyst from Northwestern University from 1955-1962.
A wide breadth of materials concerning organization with which Maria Jolas was involved are included with the James Joyce Subject Files. The Memorial Fund, specifically, was organized by Jolas in New York after Joyce's death to support his widow and children. More scholarly groups such as the James Joyce Society, the James Joyce Foundation, and the James Joyce Centre sent their publications and minutes to Jolas for many years. The Symposia, sponsored by the James Joyce Foundation at the University of Tulsa, began in Dublin in 1967. Maria was active in many of these meeting during the 1970s, and even served as coordinator for the 1975 symposium in Paris. Her planning materials for that meeting are included here along with souvenirs and documents from many of the other symposia. The documentation covering various exhibits on Joyce includes materials tracing the development of the famous display which Maria Jolas organized at La Hune gallery in Paris in 1949. Surviving from this exhibit are lists of Joyce's effects gathered after his death, and catalogs of materials offered for sale. This exhibit traveled to the Institute of Contemporary Arts in London in 1950 before many of the items were acquired by the State University of New York at Buffalo. Jolas also kept ephemera on theatrical productions of Joyce texts, musical settings of his work, monuments dedicated to Joyce, and collections of Joyce material in the United States. Transcripts from several different radio broadcasts profiling Joyce are files here, as well. Her clippings from a wide variety of printed sources have been arranged by subject, except when they were received as integral parts of other subject files.
Subject Files concerning the following persons and subjects contain miscellaneous personal items: Amerindians history, Noam Chomsky, Jacques Jolas, Lucie Léon, André Masson, Nathalie Sarraute, Pierre Vidal-Naquet, and Jean Wahl.
Series XI, Personal Papers, contains various effects found among Maria Jolas' papers. Similar to Eugène Jolas' personal papers, this series contain some legal documents (including a marriage certificate and wills) and financial documents. Three special groups of materials merit individual note. Filed here are materials documenting the running of the École bilingue de Neuilly. Extant are an account book, letters to parents, insurance policies and legal documents, many dating from the final days of the school's existence. Items relating to Maria Jolas' involvement with a service organization for French citizens in New York during World War II, the cantine La Marseillaise, include photographs and programs. Also included here are records relating to a landlord-tenant dispute referred to by Maria Jolas as "L'Affaire Hébert."
A number of interviews with Maria Jolas are found in among the personal papers here. Most of these were conducted during her later years by, among others, David Hayman, Hugh Kenner, Ellis Dillon, and Nathalie Sarraute. In addition, a large scrapbook containing photographs and notes about many of Maria Jolas' wartime activities is housed here.
The third subgroup consists of two series documenting the life of transition magazine and press. Items found here date almost entirely after World War II, because the original transition archives were lost after the Jolases had to leave France in 1940.
Series XII, General Office Files, contains legal and financial papers and material intended for general consideration in transition publications. Among the later are submissions from Anthony Borrow, Paul Eluard, Eugène Jolas, Norman MacLeod, and Gil Orlovitz. General correspondence includes letters from Marcel Duchamp, Georges Duthuit, Faber & Faber, Carola Giedion-Welcker, James Laughlin, Clémence Ramnoux and James Johnson Sweeney.
Series XIII, Imprints, is divided into specific titles published or planned by transition press. The James Joyce Yearbook includes typescripts drafts of all the articles which appeared in the volume (save for Paul Léon's "In Memory of Joyce"), along with a few submissions intended for later Yearbooks. Among the correspondence directed to this specific project are letters from Hermann Broch, Kees van Hoek, John Slocum, and Roland von Weber. Manuscripts included in the Transition Anthology are exclusively typescript resettings of works published in the original transition review, along with a few items received for consideration in the late 1940s. Material filed with the Vertical Yearbook includes letters from Kay Boyle, Amy Bonner, Padraic Colum, Ralph Gustaffson, and Marsden Hartley.